<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Nate Dobbins writes things.</title>
    <generator uri="https://gohugo.io">Hugo</generator>
    <link>https://natedobbins.net</link>
    <language>en-us</language>
    
    
    <updated>Mon, 30 Nov 2015 00:00:00 UTC</updated>
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Adjusting and Batu Caves</title>
      <link>https://natedobbins.net/travel/adjusting-and-batu-caves.html</link>
      
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Nov 2015</pubDate>
      <author>Nate Dobbins</author>
      <guid>https://natedobbins.net/travel/adjusting-and-batu-caves.html</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve been in Kuala Lumpur for just under two weeks now, and I&amp;rsquo;m settling into a pretty comfortable routine. I usually divide my day into three parts: in one part I explore a new part of the city, in another I head to the library to code or read, and in the last I relax. In between I find some food. I switch up the arrangement of the parts each day. Just having a routine is nice, though, and it&amp;rsquo;s helping me adjust pretty well. In no particular order, here are some thoughts on adapting to various aspects of life in Malaysia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;language:8b21b83e3eb70520743ff76bb4cc09d3&#34;&gt;Language&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Getting down the basics of Bahasa Malay has been straightforward. Word order is subject-verb-object like English. It also borrows a lot of words from English (this is where Malay branches apart from Indonesian, which is closely related but borrows from Dutch). The writing system is &lt;strong&gt;very&lt;/strong&gt; phonetic, which is almost jarring coming from English. Most words are pronounced exactly how you&amp;rsquo;d guess when reading them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only problem is that almost everyone here speaks English (and I&amp;rsquo;m so white), so everyone defaults to English. That&amp;rsquo;s probably a good thing though, because I&amp;rsquo;d be lost beyond the basics. My aunt was right, though, when she said that most people would probably be thankful when I put a small effort into using Malay. Usually I just slip in a &lt;em&gt;terima kasih&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;selamat pagi&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;food:8b21b83e3eb70520743ff76bb4cc09d3&#34;&gt;Food&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It can&amp;rsquo;t be overstated how good the food is. And the food stalls and cafés are neverending! Just walking down random streets, I&amp;rsquo;ll often unintentionally wander into big street markets lined with the most wonderful-smelling food I could imagine. I&amp;rsquo;m glad I have another couple months in KL, because I&amp;rsquo;ve barely scratched the surface yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;getting-around:8b21b83e3eb70520743ff76bb4cc09d3&#34;&gt;Getting around&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So far, I&amp;rsquo;ve used the train to get from the airport to the city center, and to get to Batu Caves (more on that below). Other than that, I&amp;rsquo;ve just walked everywhere. Getting around on foot is pretty easy, but there are some areas where sidewalks are a little weird. Sometimes they&amp;rsquo;ll just end, or they&amp;rsquo;ll merge into the road. For awhile I would get confused and not know how to keep going in the general direction I was trying to go, until I realized that people would just walk on the road. This happens even on bigger roads where traffic is flying by, so it took me a bit to get used to, but now I&amp;rsquo;m on board. It&amp;rsquo;s evened out by the fact that drivers often park partially on the sidewalk, and motorcyclists (who are numerous!) often &lt;em&gt;drive&lt;/em&gt; on the sidewalks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve explored just about everywhere within a three kilometer radius of my hostel, so over the next couple weeks I&amp;rsquo;m going to start using the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.gokl.com.my/&#34;&gt;Go-KL&lt;/a&gt; city bus (because it&amp;rsquo;s free!) to start exploring more of the city.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;weather:8b21b83e3eb70520743ff76bb4cc09d3&#34;&gt;Weather&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The weather has been beautiful. In the morning it&amp;rsquo;s usually around 70 degrees and clear. From around 11 to 4 it gets very hot, and then it often rains in the late afternoon and evening. As I&amp;rsquo;m writing this, I&amp;rsquo;m just getting dried off, because even though an umbrella was the first thing I bought here, I never have the sense to bring my umbrella when I go out in the morning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;getting-connected:8b21b83e3eb70520743ff76bb4cc09d3&#34;&gt;Getting connected&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since I don&amp;rsquo;t have mobile data or a phone plan, I&amp;rsquo;ve been completely relient on wifi to stay connected. So far it&amp;rsquo;s proven pretty simple. The wifi at the hostel is good. The library also has wifi, although it&amp;rsquo;s not quite as reliable. Regardless, I haven&amp;rsquo;t run into any issues with needing internet and not being able to get it. I have three different mapping applications on my phone, and all three have the ability to download maps for offline use, which is killer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;batu-caves:8b21b83e3eb70520743ff76bb4cc09d3&#34;&gt;Batu Caves&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This morning I packed up a bag and hopped on the KTM Komuter red line heading north for Batu Caves. The caves are sunken into a giant limestone hill, and they&amp;rsquo;re marked by the statue of the Hindu Lord Murugan:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5777/23418089165_bc7f5bf939_c.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;It&amp;#39;s the tallest statue in Malaysia and the second tallest statue of a Hindu deity in the world.&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
        It&amp;#39;s the tallest statue in Malaysia and the second tallest statue of a Hindu deity in the world.
        
            
        
        &lt;/p&gt; 
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s one main cave, two slightly lesser ones, and many smaller caves. They&amp;rsquo;re filled with various shrines and smaller statues. To get to the main cave you have to climb up a steep flight of stairs (pictured above behind Murugan). Inside the main cave there&amp;rsquo;s a series of three large caverns, each with a shrine. The second cavern has a small crevice in the roof where light peeps through, and the third has a &lt;em&gt;huge&lt;/em&gt; opening through which the sky lights the cave. There&amp;rsquo;s also water seeping through the openings, dripping on unsuspecting heads at various points throughout the cave. There are also a few hens and pigeons scampering about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are the stairs leading up to the third cavern in the main cave:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;https://farm1.staticflickr.com/739/23122380170_23d3eeb083_z.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Inside the main cave.&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
        Inside the main cave.
        
            
        
        &lt;/p&gt; 
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Along the walkway outside the caves, there are lots of temples and galleries, lots of pigeons and monkeys, and lots of restaurants. I had lunch at a small Indian café, which seemed to insist on Coca-Cola with every dish, so I had a Coke. Outside there was a blue-and-gold macaw and a sulphur-crested cockatoo perched on a branch. They clearly weren&amp;rsquo;t wild, but they weren&amp;rsquo;t exactly pets, and it struck me how colorful and shiny their feathers were.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The full Batu Caves photo album is &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/133041204@N06/albums/72157661786697196&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Arrival and KL Bird Park</title>
      <link>https://natedobbins.net/travel/arrival-and-kl-bird-park.html</link>
      
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Nov 2015</pubDate>
      <author>Nate Dobbins</author>
      <guid>https://natedobbins.net/travel/arrival-and-kl-bird-park.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I landed in Kuala Lumpur on Friday afternoon. The flights were excellent; Asian airlines always seem to me much nicer than American ones. From the airport I took a 30 minute train ride into KL&amp;rsquo;s Old City Centre district, and struggled for a couple hours to find my hostel in the rain. Once I did, I had to quickly figure out how to get cash, where to find food and an umbrella, and how to use my voltage converter to charge my phone. It was a rough first night, and I wasn&amp;rsquo;t as prepared as I should&amp;rsquo;ve been.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First impressions die hard (or something); everyday since has been great. The next day I woke up early to clear skies and had a delicious breakfast and tea at the hostel. I started exploring by foot and found that the traffic and sidewalks are much more manageable in the mornings. I found the beautiful &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Merdeka_Square,_Kuala_Lumpur&#34;&gt;Dataran Merdeka&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; (Independence Square), where Malaysian independence from Britain was declared in 1957. It&amp;rsquo;s surrounded by lots of really neat old colonial buildings. I also found a public library where I&amp;rsquo;ve been spending some time the last few days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ventured to the west side of the district, and found &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lake_Gardens,_Kuala_Lumpur&#34;&gt;Taman Tasik Perdana&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; (Lake Gardens), a giant park which contains—among other things—the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/133041204@N06/22793572549/in/album-72157660736018089/lightbox/&#34;&gt;National Planetarium&lt;/a&gt; and the KL Bird Park. &lt;strong&gt;Kuala Lumpur has a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.klbirdpark.com/&#34;&gt;bird park&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/strong&gt; There&amp;rsquo;s an entrance fee, so I came back a couple days later prepared to spend a whole morning there. Here are some pictures I took:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;https://farm1.staticflickr.com/575/22873062947_ed4c2abcf7_z.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;A playful red lorikeet in the World of Parrots area.&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
        A playful red lorikeet in the World of Parrots area.
        
            
        
        &lt;/p&gt; 
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5680/22899442319_f6b44eea17_z.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&amp;#34;Hey Frank, didja hear the one about the deaf cockatoo? Neither did he. /(^o^)/&amp;#34;&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
        &amp;#34;Hey Frank, didja hear the one about the deaf cockatoo? Neither did he. /(^o^)/&amp;#34;
        
            
        
        &lt;/p&gt; 
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;https://farm1.staticflickr.com/699/22639075334_a588248774_z.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;The hornbills were one the most interesting birds there. I&amp;#39;d never seen one before.&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
        The hornbills were one the most interesting birds there. I&amp;#39;d never seen one before.
        
            
        
        &lt;/p&gt; 
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Right after I took the picture above, a couple people approached me and asked if I&amp;rsquo;d be interested in doing an interview. They were filming some sort of Malaysia PSA, as best as I can tell. They were incredibly nice, and asked a lot about where I was from and what I thought about Kuala Lumpur.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5819/22639064524_887d93cae6_z.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;This grey whistled with me for a bit.&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
        This grey whistled with me for a bit.
        
            
        
        &lt;/p&gt; 
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The full album of photos I took at KL Bird Park is &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/133041204@N06/albums/72157661467887295&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I haven&amp;rsquo;t ventured too far outside the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki/Kuala_Lumpur/Central&#34;&gt;Old City Centre&lt;/a&gt; yet. There&amp;rsquo;s so much to see on every block that there&amp;rsquo;s no need to! Some more pictures are &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/133041204@N06/albums/72157660736018089&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other things of note:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Traffic is crazy. I don&amp;rsquo;t remember it being like this in Phnom Penh. Trying to cross the street is terrifying (even at a crosswalk).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The markets and the food are amazing. Just as cool (and cheap!) as they&amp;rsquo;re reputed to be. And I haven&amp;rsquo;t even been to any night markets yet, which KL is known for.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I wasn&amp;rsquo;t sure what to expect from my first time staying in a hostel. My room is tiny and windowless, the showers are cold, and the building is more than a bit rundown. But the proprieters and other guests have all been quite nice, there&amp;rsquo;s free breakfast and coffee and tea, the building is air conditioned, it&amp;rsquo;s centrally located, and it feels safe and secure. And regardless, the price of hostels here is incredibly low for what you get, so I&amp;rsquo;m very happy so far.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Do yourself a favor and don&amp;rsquo;t look at &lt;a href=&#34;http://fahrinfo.vbb.de/bin/help.exe/dn?L=vs_mobilitymap&amp;amp;tpl=fullmap&amp;amp;tabApp=show&#34;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&#34;http://brunoimbrizi.com/experiments/#/07&#34;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; if you have things to do.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    
  </channel>
</rss>

