<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Nate Dobbins writes things.</title>
    <generator uri="https://gohugo.io">Hugo</generator>
    <link>https://natedobbins.net</link>
    <language>en-us</language>
    
    
    <updated>Tue, 10 Jan 2017 00:00:00 UTC</updated>
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Less Trash</title>
      <link>https://natedobbins.net/weblog/less-trash.html</link>
      
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Jan 2017</pubDate>
      <author>Nate Dobbins</author>
      <guid>https://natedobbins.net/weblog/less-trash.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I think this year I&amp;rsquo;m going to try to transition to being entirely zero waste. For a while I&amp;rsquo;ve been following &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.trashisfortossers.com/&#34;&gt;a blog&lt;/a&gt; run by a woman who lives in New York City about trying to live a zero waste lifestyle, and she makes it seem not-crushingly-difficult.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since I moved to my current apartment last year, I&amp;rsquo;ve started composting thanks to an organics drop-off site run by the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.macgrove.org/organics&#34;&gt;MacGrove&lt;/a&gt; community council, that&amp;rsquo;s helpfully only a couple blocks from me. Next week St. Paul will start using the wheeled recycling bins that were dropped off last month &amp;ndash; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.stpaul.gov/departments/public-works/recycling-and-waste-reduction/recycling-cart-transition#materials&#34;&gt;will start accepting a few new materials&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; which will be nice (even if I still have to haul my building&amp;rsquo;s recycling to the curb every week *grumble* *grumble*).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve half-assedly moved in this direction, but I figure I might as well make an attempt at doing the full thing. I think I&amp;rsquo;ll probably mostly fail, but even if I can produce a little less trash, that&amp;rsquo;s okay.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    
    
    <item>
      <title>What I Read in 2016</title>
      <link>https://natedobbins.net/books/what-i-read-in-2016.html</link>
      
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Jan 2017</pubDate>
      <author>Nate Dobbins</author>
      <guid>https://natedobbins.net/books/what-i-read-in-2016.html</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;In the first part of 2016 &amp;ndash; when I was &lt;a href=&#34;/travel/&#34;&gt;traveling&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; I read a handful of books via Overdrive, but sometime in February my library card expired so that put a stop to that. But once I was back I got back in the habit, and I&amp;rsquo;d meant to start writing posts about some of the books that I read, but that didn&amp;rsquo;t happen, so I decided to write up this summary of what I read this year. (I was inspired to start writing about what I&amp;rsquo;m reading by &lt;a href=&#34;https://sivers.org/book&#34;&gt;Derek Sivers&amp;rsquo;s book notes&lt;/a&gt;, so the style of this may shamelessly resemble his style.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;the-list:b086e0fe5253a77279ff4661a09d5990&#34;&gt;The List&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;musicophilia-by-oliver-sacks-2007:b086e0fe5253a77279ff4661a09d5990&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Musicophilia&lt;/em&gt; by Oliver Sacks (2007)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, I&amp;rsquo;d only had a passing knowledge of Oliver Sacks (from hearing him on &lt;a href=&#34;https://radiolab.org&#34;&gt;Radiolab&lt;/a&gt;) before he died in 2015. When he died the first place I read about him at length was from my friend Abir&amp;rsquo;s Facebook post, which I think was a link to &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nytimes.com/2015/08/31/science/oliver-sacks-dies-at-82-neurologist-and-author-explored-the-brains-quirks.html&#34;&gt;a NYTimes piece&lt;/a&gt;, from where I jumped into &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.theatlantic.com/health/archive/2015/08/the-oliver-sacks-reading-list/401993/&#34;&gt;The Atlantic&amp;rsquo;s reading list&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I started traveling I decided to read his books, and the first one that I found available on Overdrive was &lt;em&gt;Musicophilia&lt;/em&gt;, which is about music and the brain. Each chapter basically goes through a patient he&amp;rsquo;d seen that has had neurological ailments related in some way to music or sound. I&amp;rsquo;d heartily recommend it to anyone interested in music or &amp;ldquo;pop neurology&amp;rdquo;. (&lt;a href=&#34;https://openlibrary.org/works/OL277255W/Musicophilia&#34;&gt;Open Library&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;watchmen-by-alan-moore-1986:b086e0fe5253a77279ff4661a09d5990&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Watchmen&lt;/em&gt; by Alan Moore (1986)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;d read Watchmen once before (maybe 10 years ago), and I can&amp;rsquo;t remember what spurred me on, but something reminded me of the book and made me want to read it again, so I did. The movie is good, but there&amp;rsquo;s so much more depth in the novel. The snippets and documents between chapters completely make the whole book. It reminded me a bit of how immersed I used to feel in video games I played was I was younger (and sort of makes me want to go back and play some of them). If anybody has any recommendations for more good graphic novels, please let me know. (&lt;a href=&#34;https://openlibrary.org/works/OL2897798W/Watchmen&#34;&gt;Open Library&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;i-am-a-strange-loop-by-douglas-hofstadter-2007:b086e0fe5253a77279ff4661a09d5990&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;I Am a Strange Loop&lt;/em&gt; by Douglas Hofstadter (2007)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2007, Hofstadter put out  &lt;em&gt;I Am a Strange Loop&lt;/em&gt; as a modern update to &amp;ndash; and more accessible version of &amp;ndash; GEB. It&amp;rsquo;s much clearer and easier to get through than GEB, but also loses something by sacrificing the depth and structure of GEB. Regardless, this is a great read that I&amp;rsquo;d recommend. For anyone interested in linguistics I also really enjoy Hofstadter&amp;rsquo;s lectures on YouTube about &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=n8m7lFQ3njk&#34;&gt;analogy&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Kr3QDMkMGmQ&#34;&gt;categories&lt;/a&gt;. (&lt;a href=&#34;https://openlibrary.org/works/OL8067922W/I_Am_a_Strange_Loop&#34;&gt;Open Library&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-dharma-bums-by-jack-kerouac-1958:b086e0fe5253a77279ff4661a09d5990&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Dharma Bums&lt;/em&gt; by Jack Kerouac (1958)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My friend Colin lent me this about a month ago, and I absolutely loved it. He said he thought I&amp;rsquo;d like it since I&amp;rsquo;d started doing some traveling and backpacking, and most all of Kerouac&amp;rsquo;s writing revolves around traveling and life on the road in some sense. I loved it so much that I recommended it to my dad, who quickly bought and read &lt;em&gt;On the Road&lt;/em&gt;, which I&amp;rsquo;m waiting to borrow from him. (&lt;a href=&#34;https://openlibrary.org/works/OL65940W/The_Dharma_Bums&#34;&gt;Open Library&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-hobbit-by-j-r-r-tolkien-1937:b086e0fe5253a77279ff4661a09d5990&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Hobbit&lt;/em&gt; by J.R.R. Tolkien (1937)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Somewhat shamefully, I&amp;rsquo;d never read &lt;em&gt;The Hobbit&lt;/em&gt; (and still haven&amp;rsquo;t read Lord of the Rings) so when I was in Kuala Lumpur I read it. There&amp;rsquo;s not much I can say that hasn&amp;rsquo;t been said about the book, other than that I wish I would&amp;rsquo;ve read it a lot sooner. (&lt;a href=&#34;https://openlibrary.org/works/OL262758W/The_Hobbit&#34;&gt;Open Library&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-man-who-mistook-his-wife-for-a-hat-by-oliver-sacks-1985:b086e0fe5253a77279ff4661a09d5990&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Man Who Mistook His Wife for a Hat&lt;/em&gt; by Oliver Sacks (1985)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since I&amp;rsquo;d loved &lt;em&gt;Musicophilia&lt;/em&gt; so much earlier in the year, I&amp;rsquo;d been wanting to read more Oliver Sacks, so when I inherited &lt;em&gt;The Man Who Mistook His Wife for a Hat&lt;/em&gt; I started reading it pretty quickly. Like &lt;em&gt;Musicophilia&lt;/em&gt;, each chapter recounts a patient that Sacks had seen, around a variety of different subjects, the first being a man who mistakes his wife for a hat. The writing isn&amp;rsquo;t quite as strong as &lt;em&gt;musicophilia&lt;/em&gt;, but the stories are great regardless. (&lt;a href=&#34;https://openlibrary.org/works/OL1811909W/The_man_who_mistook_his_wife_for_a_hat_and_other_clinical_tales&#34;&gt;Open Library&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-gunslinger-by-stephen-king-1982:b086e0fe5253a77279ff4661a09d5990&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Gunslinger&lt;/em&gt; by Stephen King (1982)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I stole a handful of my brother&amp;rsquo;s books that were left in my parents&amp;rsquo; basement, mostly Stephen King books. This one, which is the first book in The Dark Tower series, was the first one I&amp;rsquo;ve read. I enjoyed it and I&amp;rsquo;m going to keep reading the series, but it was a little slow. I&amp;rsquo;m not quite sure what to make of it, but for whatever reason it left me really excited to read more in the series regardless. (&lt;a href=&#34;https://openlibrary.org/works/OL81628W/The_Gunslinger&#34;&gt;Open Library&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;hegemony-or-survival-by-noam-chomsky-2003:b086e0fe5253a77279ff4661a09d5990&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Hegemony or Survival&lt;/em&gt; by Noam Chomsky (2003)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve only started listening to and reading some of Chomsky&amp;rsquo;s interviews and essays in the last couple years. &lt;em&gt;Hegemony or Survival&lt;/em&gt; is the first book of his that I&amp;rsquo;ve read. From &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hegemony_or_Survival&#34;&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chomsky&amp;rsquo;s main argument in Hegemony or Survival is that the socio-economic elite who control the United States have pursued an &amp;ldquo;Imperial Grand Strategy&amp;rdquo; since the end of World War II in order to maintain global hegemony through military, political and economic means. He argues that in doing so they have repeatedly shown a total disregard for democracy and human rights, in stark contrast to the US government&amp;rsquo;s professed support for those values. Furthermore, he argues that this continual pursuit of global hegemony now threatens the existence of the human species itself because of the increasing proliferation of weapons of mass destruction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Drawing historical examples from 1945 through to 2003 to support his argument, Chomsky looks at the US government&amp;rsquo;s support for regimes responsible for mass human rights abuses (including ethnic cleansing and genocide), namely El Salvador, Colombia, Turkey, Israel, Egypt, South Africa and Indonesia. He also discusses US support for militant dissident groups widely considered &amp;ldquo;terrorists&amp;rdquo;, particularly in Nicaragua and Cuba, as well as direct military interventions, such as the Vietnam War, NATO bombing of Yugoslavia, Afghan War and Iraq War, in order to further its power and grasp of resources. In doing so, he highlights that US foreign policy – whether controlled by Republican or Democratic administrations – still follows the same agenda of gaining access to lucrative resources and maintaining US world dominance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s a dense book, and I&amp;rsquo;m still digesting it, but it&amp;rsquo;s mostly a more in-depth version of what you&amp;rsquo;d expect from a Chomsky interview. I think if I re-read it at some point I&amp;rsquo;ll probably find a lot more that I didn&amp;rsquo;t absorb on first read. (&lt;a href=&#34;https://openlibrary.org/works/OL71680W/Hegemony_or_survival&#34;&gt;Open Library&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;casting-fortune-by-john-m-ford-1989:b086e0fe5253a77279ff4661a09d5990&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Casting Fortune&lt;/em&gt; by John M. Ford (1989)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Probably about 15 years ago, my great grandma was moving out of her house, and we were free to take whatever we wanted from the house, so I took a fantasy story anthology. The first story was &lt;em&gt;Green is the Color&lt;/em&gt; by &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_M._Ford&#34;&gt;John M. Ford&lt;/a&gt;. I only ever ended up reading a handful of the stories in the book, but &lt;em&gt;Green is the Color&lt;/em&gt; became one of my favorite fantasy stories. It took me a long time, but a couple years ago I finally got around to ordering some more John M. Ford books, and this year I finally read this one. (And it only somewhat counts because &lt;em&gt;Casting Fortune&lt;/em&gt; is made up of 3 short stories, one of which is &lt;em&gt;Green is the Color&lt;/em&gt;. I really just wanted an excuse to re-read it.) A couple years ago I found out that Ford lived in Minnesota, but died in 2006.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of the stories in &lt;em&gt;Casting Fortune&lt;/em&gt; take place in a shared (between authors) fantasy world called Liavek. I haven&amp;rsquo;t read any stories other than Ford&amp;rsquo;s, but &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Liavek#Liavek&#34;&gt;the setting&lt;/a&gt; is my favorite part of the stories. I would definitely recommend for fans of short fantasy stories.(&lt;a href=&#34;https://openlibrary.org/works/OL3922331W/Casting_fortune&#34;&gt;Open Library&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;1q84-by-haruki-murakami-2009-2010:b086e0fe5253a77279ff4661a09d5990&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;1Q84&lt;/em&gt; by Haruki Murakami (2009-2010)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can&amp;rsquo;t remember where I first heard of Haruki Murakami, but everything I heard about him seemed to indicate that I should read his stuff. It was worth it; I think 1Q84 is my favorite book I read this year. The plot is really complex and weird, revolving around a cult, two parallel realities, and lots more (it&amp;rsquo;s tough to mention much without giving a lot away). I thought the ending was a little disappointing but overall I loved it. I&amp;rsquo;d definitely like to read more Murakami in 2017. If anyone has recommendations for his other books (or similar stories from other authors), I&amp;rsquo;d love to hear them! (&lt;a href=&#34;https://openlibrary.org/works/OL15933475W/1Q84&#34;&gt;Open Library&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-first-half-of-american-gods-by-neil-gaiman-2001:b086e0fe5253a77279ff4661a09d5990&#34;&gt;The first half of &lt;em&gt;American Gods&lt;/em&gt; by Neil Gaiman (2001)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;d wanted to read Neil Gaiman for a long time, and &lt;em&gt;American Gods&lt;/em&gt; was one option available in Overdrive was I was traveling. Unfortunately, I only got about halfway through it when my library card expired. But I loved what I&amp;rsquo;d read so far, so I&amp;rsquo;m planning on starting again at some point, and I&amp;rsquo;d also really like to read other Gaiman. (&lt;a href=&#34;https://openlibrary.org/works/OL679360W/American_Gods&#34;&gt;Open Library&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-first-half-of-harry-potter-and-the-methods-of-rationality-by-eliezer-yudkowsky-2010-2015:b086e0fe5253a77279ff4661a09d5990&#34;&gt;The first half of  &lt;em&gt;Harry Potter and the Methods of Rationality&lt;/em&gt; by Eliezer Yudkowsky (2010-2015)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I read some of HPMOR, and enjoyed it a lot, but didn&amp;rsquo;t finish it for some reason. I&amp;rsquo;m planning on coming back to it at some point. It&amp;rsquo;s a fanfiction of Harry Potter where his aunt marries a scientist, and Harry is raised in a happy and loving household. He goes to Hogwarts and tries to understand magic using the scientific method. (&lt;a href=&#34;http://hpmor.com/&#34;&gt;Website&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-if-by-randall-munroe-2014:b086e0fe5253a77279ff4661a09d5990&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;What If?&lt;/em&gt; by Randall Munroe (2014)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I spent most of my New Year&amp;rsquo;s weekend watching the Downton Alley marathon on TPT 2 (interspersed with a couple Sherlock episodes), and broke it up by reading &lt;em&gt;What If?&lt;/em&gt;. I&amp;rsquo;d bought the book when it came out in 2014, read a couple chapters, stuck it in my bathroom for toilet reading, and never read another page. So I started it again on New Year&amp;rsquo;s Eve and was able to get through it in a day. (If you haven&amp;rsquo;t heard of &lt;em&gt;What If?&lt;/em&gt;, check out &lt;a href=&#34;https://what-if.xkcd.com/&#34;&gt;the blog&lt;/a&gt;. The premise is pretty thoroughly covered by the subtitle: &amp;ldquo;Serious Scientific Answers to Absurd Hypothetical Questions&amp;rdquo;.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Suffice it to say, this book is awesome &amp;ndash; and a quick read &amp;ndash; and if I was tasked with getting anybody more interested in science, I&amp;rsquo;d give them this book. Check out the &lt;a href=&#34;https://books.google.com/books/about/What_If.html?id=iXoOAwAAQBAJ#toc&#34;&gt;table of contents&lt;/a&gt; if you&amp;rsquo;re intrigued. (&lt;a href=&#34;https://openlibrary.org/works/OL17095301W/What_If&#34;&gt;Open Library&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;what-i-want-to-read-in-2017:b086e0fe5253a77279ff4661a09d5990&#34;&gt;What I want to read in 2017&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Right now I&amp;rsquo;m reading &lt;em&gt;The Best American Short Stories of 2013&lt;/em&gt;, which my grandma lent me. Over Christmas my uncle lent me &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/627639.Za_to_pek_Za_to_pek_Za_to_pek_&#34;&gt;a book about Emil Zátopek&lt;/a&gt;, a Czech distance runner. I also got the second Dark Tower book, &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Dark_Tower_II:_The_Drawing_of_the_Three&#34;&gt;The Drawing of the Three&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;, for Christmas. My friend Keith recently lent me the Lonely Planet guide to &lt;em&gt;Peru&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are a few other books I recently inherited: &lt;em&gt;Consciousness Explained&lt;/em&gt; by Daniel Dennett, &lt;em&gt;Society of Mind&lt;/em&gt; by Marvin Minsky, and &lt;em&gt;A World of Ideas&lt;/em&gt; by Bill Moyers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I recently picked up the Unix-themed &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.humblebundle.com/books/unix-book-bundle&#34;&gt;Humble Book Bundle&lt;/a&gt; of ebooks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are some writers that I&amp;rsquo;ve never delved into that I&amp;rsquo;d like to: Camus, Dostoyevsky, Gwen Ifill, and Neal Stephenson, to name a few. I&amp;rsquo;ve been lucky to have been gifted and lent a lot of really great books lately; if anybody has any recommendations, I&amp;rsquo;d love to hear them!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Sunk Costs</title>
      <link>https://natedobbins.net/audio/sunk-costs.html</link>
      <enclosure url="https://natedobbins.net/audio/sunk-costs.ogg" type="audio/ogg" />
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Dec 2016</pubDate>
      <author>Nate Dobbins</author>
      <guid>https://natedobbins.net/audio/sunk-costs.html</guid>
      <description>

&lt;audio controls&gt;
  &lt;source src=&#34;/audio/sunk-costs.ogg&#34; type=&#34;audio/ogg&#34;&gt;
  &lt;a href=&#34;/audio/sunk-costs.ogg&#34;&gt;Download audio file.&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/audio&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The dialogue is from the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Foundation_series#Radio_adaptation&#34;&gt;radio adaptation of Isaac Asimov&amp;rsquo;s Foundation trilogy&lt;/a&gt;, originally broadcast on BBC Radio 3 in 1973, now in the public domain. The full audio series is available &lt;a href=&#34;https://archive.org/details/IsaacAsimov-TheFoundationTrilogy&#34;&gt;on the Internet Archive&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s very apparent clipping on the guitar tracks that I couldn&amp;rsquo;t figure out, so I just rolled with it. I wrote and recorded some lyrics for it, but I just didn&amp;rsquo;t like how it came out. The higher, two-note guitar track was my first time recording with an E-Bow, which was fun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;software:96887e21471164fc81ff5c77e90d2e5b&#34;&gt;Software&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://ubuntustudio.org/&#34;&gt;Ubuntu Studio&lt;/a&gt; 16.04, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.audacityteam.org/&#34;&gt;Audacity&lt;/a&gt; 2.1.0, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.hydrogen-music.org/hcms/&#34;&gt;Hydrogen&lt;/a&gt; 0.9.6.1&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;hardware:96887e21471164fc81ff5c77e90d2e5b&#34;&gt;Hardware&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mexican Fender Stratocaster, 2012 &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/ThinkPad_X1_Carbon&#34;&gt;Lenovo ThinkPad X1 Carbon&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/EBow&#34;&gt;E-Bow&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pcmag.com/article2/0,2817,2401602,00.asp&#34;&gt;M-Audio FastTrack&lt;/a&gt; audio interface, Behringer CO600 chorus pedal&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Peaking Inside a MacBook Pro</title>
      <link>https://natedobbins.net/computers/peaking-inside-a-macbook-pro.html</link>
      
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Dec 2016</pubDate>
      <author>Nate Dobbins</author>
      <guid>https://natedobbins.net/computers/peaking-inside-a-macbook-pro.html</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Last week a co-worker accidentally dropped her 2010 Macbook Pro 13&amp;rdquo;. It was in a bag, and only dropped a short distance to the ground, so the case wasn&amp;rsquo;t damaged. But upon opening it and trying to power it on, it wouldn&amp;rsquo;t boot. It gave three short beeps, then a pause, then three more beeps, over and over.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Luckily apple.com has &lt;a href=&#34;https://support.apple.com/en-us/HT202768&#34;&gt;a support thread&lt;/a&gt; explaining that the RAM wasn&amp;rsquo;t passing an integrity check, probably meaning it had become dislodged or something. I was a bit excited because I&amp;rsquo;ve never looked inside a Macbook before.&lt;a class=&#34;ref&#34; href=&#34;#ref-1&#34; id=&#34;cit-1&#34;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We didn&amp;rsquo;t have a screwdriver in the office small enough to take out the tiny screws holding together the MacBook case, but I eventually got it open using a paring knife we had in the kitchen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://c5.staticflickr.com/1/557/30928488924_4954859664_b.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Under the hood of a 2010 MacBook Pro 13&amp;#34;&#34; /&gt;
  
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
      &lt;h4 class=&#34;alt&#34;&gt;Under the hood of a 2010 MacBook Pro 13&amp;#34;&lt;/h4&gt;
      
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In the photo above the memory is sitting in the center-right &amp;ndash; under the white label with a barcode.&lt;a class=&#34;ref&#34; href=&#34;#ref-2&#34; id=&#34;cit-2&#34;&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;
 There are two small levers on either side of the RAM that can be pulled apart to takes out the RAM. It pops out at an angle about 45 degrees vertically from the surface of the motherboard, and goes back in the same way, giving a nice audible click when it&amp;rsquo;s seated back in place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;d never looked inside a Macbook before and was excited to take a look at the esteemed build quality, and I wasn&amp;rsquo;t let down. That this was a 6 &lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; year old laptop still chugging along &amp;ndash; not to mention being easy to diagnose and repair a hardware issue &amp;ndash; is a testament to how well put together these are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;notes:aa8367581fca9c38fb003bafee883020&#34;&gt;Notes&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li id=&#34;ref-1&#34;&gt;Besides watching &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/user/rossmanngroup&#34;&gt;Louis Rossmann&lt;/a&gt; videos. &lt;a class=&#34;cit&#34; href=&#34;#cit-1&#34;&gt;&amp;crarr;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li id=&#34;ref-2&#34;&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s hard to tell, but if you look closely you can make out that the RAM is still slightly twisted out of its slot in the photo. &lt;a class=&#34;cit&#34; href=&#34;#cit-2&#34;&gt;&amp;crarr;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Swimming</title>
      <link>https://natedobbins.net/audio/swimming.html</link>
      <enclosure url="https://natedobbins.net/audio/swimming.ogg" type="audio/ogg" />
      <pubDate>Sun, 18 Dec 2016</pubDate>
      <author>Nate Dobbins</author>
      <guid>https://natedobbins.net/audio/swimming.html</guid>
      <description>

&lt;audio controls&gt;
  &lt;source src=&#34;/audio/swimming.ogg&#34; type=&#34;audio/ogg&#34;&gt;
  &lt;a href=&#34;/audio/swimming.ogg&#34;&gt;Download audio file.&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/audio&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I recorded this earlier this year when I was &lt;a href=&#34;/travel/two-months-on-malaysian-islands.html&#34;&gt;in George Town&lt;/a&gt; on the island Penang in Malaysia, and forgot about it. I was learning to use an audio programming program called Sonic Pi.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;software:ca00123262fa89a84d50980f0a7382a3&#34;&gt;Software&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://ubuntustudio.org/&#34;&gt;Ubuntu Studio&lt;/a&gt; 16.04, &lt;a href=&#34;http://sonic-pi.net/&#34;&gt;Sonic Pi&lt;/a&gt; 2.9.0, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.audacityteam.org/&#34;&gt;Audacity&lt;/a&gt; 2.1.0&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;hardware:ca00123262fa89a84d50980f0a7382a3&#34;&gt;Hardware&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2012 &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/ThinkPad_X1_Carbon&#34;&gt;Lenovo ThinkPad X1 Carbon&lt;/a&gt;, a pair of headphones I&amp;rsquo;d bought at a George Town mall that worked for about a week&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Keyboards</title>
      <link>https://natedobbins.net/computers/keyboards.html</link>
      
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Dec 2016</pubDate>
      <author>Nate Dobbins</author>
      <guid>https://natedobbins.net/computers/keyboards.html</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h1 id=&#34;waiting:061ed8642bb5183054a15f89090ff532&#34;&gt;Waiting&amp;hellip;&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the last 3 or so years, I&amp;rsquo;ve been passively searching for a really good keyboard, since I spend a lot of time typing. Mainly my wants were for it to be ergonomic (split) and to have mechanical keyswitches. After my brother semi-recently started having major &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Repetitive_strain_injury&#34;&gt;RSI&lt;/a&gt; issues, my search has been kicked into high gear. Herein I&amp;rsquo;ll attempt to document some thoughts on the keyboards I considered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;keyboardio:061ed8642bb5183054a15f89090ff532&#34;&gt;Keyboardio&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first keyboard that really caught my attention was &lt;a href=&#34;https://shop.keyboard.io/&#34;&gt;Keyboardio&lt;/a&gt;, mainly because of the really great &lt;a href=&#34;http://blog.fsck.com/2013/12/better-and-better-keyboards.html&#34;&gt;blog post&lt;/a&gt; from Jesse Vincent&amp;ndash;one of the two founders&amp;ndash;describing the different iterations he went through while initially designing it. It was funded as a Kickstarter project&amp;ndash;and easily met it&amp;rsquo;s goal&amp;ndash;but unfortunately has been stuck in design and manufacturing stages for a long time, and is still in pre-order status, expected to be delivered in Q1 2017.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;https://cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/0920/0728/products/looking_across_from_front_l_corner_grande.jpg?v=1437001156&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Fortunately the team has been really open about the entire process, and has &lt;a href=&#34;http://blog.keyboard.io/&#34;&gt;written extensively&lt;/a&gt; about it, including the various decisions that have gone into design, and hurdles they&amp;rsquo;ve had to jump in working with hardware manufacturers. It&amp;rsquo;s been a super fascinating process to follow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main reason I didn&amp;rsquo;t buy one was because of the price, $329 (was $250 for Kickstarter backers if I recall correctly), which is more than I&amp;rsquo;d like to pay.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;ergodox:061ed8642bb5183054a15f89090ff532&#34;&gt;Ergodox&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;figure class=&#34;right large&#34;&gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;https://www.ergodox.io/img/ErgoDox-original-min.png&#34; alt=&#34;Ergodox&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The next keyboard I seriously considered was the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ergodox.io/&#34;&gt;Ergodox&lt;/a&gt;. The design of the Ergodox is really cool (and freely licensed!), but it takes a little more than &amp;ldquo;here&amp;rsquo;s some money&amp;rdquo; to procure one. They generally have to be bought as a kit, and you have to buy the kit as part of a &amp;ldquo;drop&amp;rdquo; (a group manufacturing deal). Then, you&amp;rsquo;ll have to do some soldering and flash the firmware onto the keyboard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This leaves a lot of room for customization (and people have made some &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.reddit.com/r/MechanicalKeyboards/search?q=ergodox&amp;amp;sort=top&amp;amp;restrict_sr=on&#34;&gt;seriously cool designs&lt;/a&gt;), and deserves a lot of credit for the DIY ethos, but it was more work than I wanted to sign up for. Then along came the &lt;a href=&#34;https://ergodox-ez.com/&#34;&gt;Ergodox EZ&lt;/a&gt;, a pre-assembled Ergodox. I would&amp;rsquo;ve leapt at this, but the price was just a little higher than I wanted to pay, because when it first became available for IndieGogo pre-order (it&amp;rsquo;s now available for regular purchase) I wasn&amp;rsquo;t employed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;kinesis-advantage:061ed8642bb5183054a15f89090ff532&#34;&gt;Kinesis Advantage&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;figure class=&#34;right&#34;&gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;https://www.kinesis-ergo.com/wp-content/uploads/2016/08/kb600-angled-cc-510x344.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Kinesis Advantage&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I haven&amp;rsquo;t really seriously considered the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.kinesis-ergo.com/shop/advantage2/&#34;&gt;Kinesis Advantage&lt;/a&gt; because of the price (are you noticing a trend?), but it&amp;rsquo;s a cool keyboard that I read about pretty extensively anyway. Kinesis has been making ergonomic keyboards with mechanical keys for longer than anyone else as far as I&amp;rsquo;m aware. Anandtech has &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.anandtech.com/show/7125/kinesis-advantage-review-longterm-evaluation&#34;&gt;a really good review&lt;/a&gt; of the Advantage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;ultimate-hacking-keyboard:061ed8642bb5183054a15f89090ff532&#34;&gt;Ultimate Hacking Keyboard&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;https://ultimatehackingkeyboard.com/&#34;&gt;Ultimate Hacking Keyboard&lt;/a&gt; is another crowdfunded one that&amp;rsquo;s still in the pre-order process (&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.crowdsupply.com/ugl/ultimate-hacking-keyboard&#34;&gt;on CrowdSupply&lt;/a&gt;, expected to ship in February).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure class=&#34;right&#34;&gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;https://ultimatehackingkeyboard.com/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/press-kit/thumbs/IMGL8954.png&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I really like the form factor of the UHK, but again, the price (currently $220, will be $250 after launch) kept me from ordering, although on this one I was pretty close.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;ibm-model-m:061ed8642bb5183054a15f89090ff532&#34;&gt;IBM Model M&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I recently inherited an &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Model_M_keyboard&#34;&gt;IBM Model M&lt;/a&gt;. I&amp;rsquo;d never used one, but I knew that they were pretty sought after for their clicky keys. (Can confirm; extremely clicky.)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/4/48/IBM_Model_M.png&#34; alt=&#34;IBM Model M&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m not using it (it&amp;rsquo;s a little &lt;em&gt;too&lt;/em&gt; clicky, it&amp;rsquo;s not split, and my laptop doesn&amp;rsquo;t have a PS/2 port), but it&amp;rsquo;s neat to have.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;microsoft-4000:061ed8642bb5183054a15f89090ff532&#34;&gt;Microsoft 4000&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At work I recently found an old Microsoft Natural Ergonomic Keyboard 4000 in the closet, and started using it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure class=&#34;right&#34;&gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;https://c7.staticflickr.com/1/666/30695061574_88441be033_z.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Microsoft Ergonomic Keyboard 4000&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s fairly comfortable, but to my surprise, it actually takes more force to push down the keys than the mechanical keyboards I&amp;rsquo;ve used. (This might not be the case with newer models, I&amp;rsquo;m guessing the one I&amp;rsquo;m using is at least 4 or 5 years old.) I&amp;rsquo;ve also come to dislike the numpad (on any keyboard, not specifically on this one), since you have to reach further for the mouse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;mistel-barocco-review:061ed8642bb5183054a15f89090ff532&#34;&gt;Mistel Barocco review&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The keyboard I eventually went with&amp;ndash;back in October&amp;ndash;was the Mistel Barocco with Cherry MX Brown switches &lt;a href=&#34;https://smile.amazon.com/Mistel-Ergonomic-Mechanical-Keyboard-Switches/dp/B01KN6LBDU?th=1&#34;&gt;from Amazon&lt;/a&gt;. The form factor is pretty similar to the Ultimate Hacking Keyboard and the Ergodox, but the price is $160, which I could stomach.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure class=&#34;left large&#34;&gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;https://c3.staticflickr.com/1/212/31440232002_e221cdff4a_c.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Mistel Barocco&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s been awesome so far. I was a little hesitant at first, because it just came out in August, and there were only a couple reviews when I bought it (still only 9 at the time of this writing), but the ones that were there were pretty thorough and enthusiastic about it. My only gripes with it are that&amp;ndash;though the two halves fit together&amp;ndash;there&amp;rsquo;s no mechanism for keeping them together, which would&amp;rsquo;ve been useful for transporting; and also that the keys aren&amp;rsquo;t backlit (although there are now backlit models available for $180). (I&amp;rsquo;ve also had issues with the left half of the keyboard not being immediately recognized after waking my laptop, but I&amp;rsquo;m fairly certain this is either being caused by my OS or the USB hub the keyboard is plugged into, or some combination thereof.) But these are minor gripes. Overall the keyboard has been awesome to use. It&amp;rsquo;s both the first ergonomic keyboard and the first mechanical keyboard that I&amp;rsquo;ve used full time, and it&amp;rsquo;s been extremely comfortable and easy to get used to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although I&amp;rsquo;d still like to try a few of the others that I mentioned (esp. Keyboardio and Ergodox), I&amp;rsquo;ve been really pleased with the Barocco, even before considering prices. I&amp;rsquo;d highly recommend it to anyone who spends a lot of time typing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;to-colemak:061ed8642bb5183054a15f89090ff532&#34;&gt;To Colemak&amp;hellip;&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another thing (besides mechanical keyswitches and a split design) that I often see mentioned in online discussions about keyboards is key layout. The argument against QWERTY usually goes that it was designed in the 19th century, and meant for typewriters, and so was designed with a set of goals and restrictions that no longer exist or don&amp;rsquo;t apply today (i.e. that letters often appearing in subsequent order shouldn&amp;rsquo;t be next to each other to prevent jamming, and that the keys in &amp;ldquo;typewriter&amp;rdquo; should be located entirely in the top row for demonstration purposes&lt;a class=&#34;ref&#34; href=&#34;#ref-1&#34; id=&#34;cit-1&#34;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;). So QWERTY is what was designed, and it&amp;rsquo;s what we still have today because it&amp;rsquo;s impractical to switch since QWERTY is what everyone has learned and gotten used to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But that hasn&amp;rsquo;t stopped individuals from coming up with new layouts and switching themselves. And people who switch often report major increases in comfort, and sometimes minor increases in typing speed. In the &amp;lsquo;30s we got &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dvorak_Simplified_Keyboard&#34;&gt;Dvorak&lt;/a&gt;, still the second most popular layout after QWERTY. In the 2000s, there have been a lot of new layouts, often designed partially or entirely by computer algorithm to optimize for things like commonly adjacent letters being placed on opposite halves, and the most common letters being on the home row. Colemak and Workman are the most popular of the more recent layouts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In November I switched to &lt;a href=&#34;https://colemak.com/&#34;&gt;Colemak&lt;/a&gt; since it&amp;rsquo;s a pretty popular layout&lt;a class=&#34;ref&#34; href=&#34;#ref-2&#34; id=&#34;cit-2&#34;&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;  (third, after QWERTY and Dvorak) so there are a lot of anecdotes and guides available from people who switched (I was especially worried about having to move things around in Vim). The first couple weeks proved to be &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; difficult. ~15 years of touch typing with QWERTY is not easily unlearned. I practiced a lot with &lt;a href=&#34;http://zty.pe/&#34;&gt;zty.pe&lt;/a&gt;, a typing game my friend Zach had shown me, and that helped a lot. After 4 weeks I was fairly comfortable with it, and had gotten close to my speed with QWERTY.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But even by only a couple weeks in, I noticed a &lt;em&gt;huge&lt;/em&gt; increase in comfort. Luckily I&amp;rsquo;ve never dealt with too much wrist pain, but at the end of some days where I&amp;rsquo;ve spent a lot of time typing, I&amp;rsquo;ve had some aches. I haven&amp;rsquo;t noticed this at all since switching to Colemak.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;and-back-again:061ed8642bb5183054a15f89090ff532&#34;&gt;&amp;hellip; and back again&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alas, all good things must come to an end. I got a job that entails working on other people&amp;rsquo;s workstations much of the time, which means I have to stick with QWERTY for the time being. Part of me is considering trying to stay proficient in both layouts, but I&amp;rsquo;m not sure it would be worth the trouble&lt;a class=&#34;ref&#34; href=&#34;#ref-3&#34; id=&#34;cit-3&#34;&gt;[3]&lt;/a&gt;. It took me about 2 days before I was back to my normal speed and comfort level with QWERTY. (I used zty.pe again to make the switch back.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;notes:061ed8642bb5183054a15f89090ff532&#34;&gt;Notes&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li id=&#34;ref-1&#34;&gt;The Colemak website has a more extensive list of complaints about &lt;a href=&#34;https://colemak.com/FAQ#What.27s_wrong_with_the_QWERTY_layout.3F&#34;&gt;QWERTY&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://colemak.com/FAQ#What.27s_wrong_with_the_Dvorak_layout.3F&#34;&gt;Dvorak&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a class=&#34;cit&#34; href=&#34;#cit-1&#34;&gt;&amp;crarr;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

  &lt;li id=&#34;ref-2&#34;&gt;Colemak (along with Dvorak) was also an option built-in to my new Barocco keyboard, although I found it easier to just use my OS&amp;rsquo;s built-in keyboard layout options. &lt;a class=&#34;cit&#34; href=&#34;#cit-2&#34;&gt;&amp;crarr;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

  &lt;li id=&#34;ref-3&#34;&gt;Though I&amp;rsquo;d be interested in &lt;a href=&#34;#contact&#34;&gt;in hearing from&lt;/a&gt; anyone who regularly moves between different layouts. &lt;a class=&#34;cit&#34; href=&#34;#cit-3&#34;&gt;&amp;crarr;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    
    
    <item>
      <title>One Year Without Work</title>
      <link>https://natedobbins.net/weblog/one-year-without-work.html</link>
      
      <pubDate>Sat, 03 Dec 2016</pubDate>
      <author>Nate Dobbins</author>
      <guid>https://natedobbins.net/weblog/one-year-without-work.html</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s now been a little over a year since I left my job to travel last November, and somehow I&amp;rsquo;ve survived. The hardest part has been the awkward confusion when someone asks what I do. I usually sort of stumble through a brief explanation that I&amp;rsquo;m taking time off to study or somesuch. Most respond with an incredulous look seeming to say either &amp;ldquo;I don&amp;rsquo;t believe you&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;this asshole definitely lives in his parents&amp;rsquo; basement.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;mental-health:fc84fea5310ea60ddb3b3c9b9d9b4ddc&#34;&gt;Mental health&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By far the biggest beneficiary of my year off has been my mental health. I can&amp;rsquo;t even begin to enunciate what a difference it makes to wake up everyday without an alarm, feeling totally refreshed and getting up to work on and learn about things that I care about. There&amp;rsquo;ve been (many) bouts of laziness, but I can confidently say I&amp;rsquo;ve learned more in the past year than in any other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&#34;left large&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://c1.staticflickr.com/6/5789/30434493360_60da40d553_z.jpg&#34;&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;I learned how to bake bread a couple weeks ago.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Besides generally feeling more relaxed, I eat better and cook better, I read a lot more, I make some of my own household products, I&amp;rsquo;ve set up a compost bin for my apartment building, I write more, I go to neighborhood council meetings, I spend more time hanging out with parrots, and on and on. Of course these are all things I &lt;em&gt;could&lt;/em&gt; have done when I worked full time, but in reality there&amp;rsquo;s no way I would have had the time and motivation. After spending 9 hours a day in an office &amp;ndash; and perhaps an extra 1-2 hours idly thinking about work &amp;ndash; I didn&amp;rsquo;t have enough motivation during the week to do much of anything other than collapse on the couch and stare at the TV. (I should note that my old job was mostly very laid back, and overall really enjoyable &amp;ndash; mostly thanks to my great co-workers. I think the key takeaway for me was that I was stuck spending 40 hours every week doing work that was ultimately not very meaningful to me.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;back-to-work:fc84fea5310ea60ddb3b3c9b9d9b4ddc&#34;&gt;Back to work&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course the sabbatical could only last so long. Over the summer when I first moved back to St. Paul, I sent out a lot of applications, and had a handful of interviews, but never got an offer. It was pretty discouraging&lt;a class=&#34;ref&#34; href=&#34;#ref-1&#34; id=&#34;cit-1&#34;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;. But then a little over a week ago, I got an email from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.jmurphyassociates.com&#34;&gt;a small Minneapolis company&lt;/a&gt; I&amp;rsquo;d applied to in May and hadn&amp;rsquo;t heard back from, asking if I&amp;rsquo;d come in for an interview. I had the interview earlier this week on Monday, accepted their offer the same day, and started on Wednesday. It was a surprise; I&amp;rsquo;d all but given up looking for a job over the summer, and had made other plans for the coming year&lt;a class=&#34;ref&#34; href=&#34;#ref-2&#34; id=&#34;cit-2&#34;&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So now I&amp;rsquo;m an IT manager. (I&amp;rsquo;m also the only IT person, so it&amp;rsquo;s not as impressive as I wish it were.) I remember being excited when I first applied for this job back in May because it&amp;rsquo;s a part time position, but I&amp;rsquo;m making about the same per-hour amount as I made in my old job, which will be plenty enough to sustain myself on, and &amp;ndash; more importantly &amp;ndash; will leave me with plenty of free time to keep doing the things I really care about, which should help me avoid the burnout I had at my old job. I only had two days to work with the person previously in my new position&lt;a class=&#34;ref&#34; href=&#34;#ref-3&#34; id=&#34;cit-3&#34;&gt;[3]&lt;/a&gt;, but it&amp;rsquo;s been enjoyable so far. In my cover letter back in May I had said that I was looking to work for a small business or nonprofit; JMA is a small business that works almost entirely with local nonprofits so I&amp;rsquo;m in a great environment with a lot of really smart, kind people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;spending:fc84fea5310ea60ddb3b3c9b9d9b4ddc&#34;&gt;Spending&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to &lt;a href=&#34;https://personalcapital.com&#34;&gt;Personal Capital&lt;/a&gt;, my total spending from November 2015 to November 2016 was $10,175, meaning I spent an average of about $848 per month.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From November to May &amp;ndash; while traveling &amp;ndash; I spent a total of $4541, or about $757 per month. From May to this November, I spent $5641, or about $940 per month. Now that the Cross Country season is over&lt;a class=&#34;ref&#34; href=&#34;#ref-4&#34; id=&#34;cit-4&#34;&gt;[4]&lt;/a&gt;, I&amp;rsquo;m planning on getting rid of my car, which should save me an extra chunk. When I stopped working last year my biggest worry was that what I had saved up wasn&amp;rsquo;t going to get me as far as I thought it would. That was completely unfounded. I&amp;rsquo;ve had a downright comfy and fulfilling year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;happiness-for-sale:fc84fea5310ea60ddb3b3c9b9d9b4ddc&#34;&gt;Happiness for sale&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reflecting on the last year, it&amp;rsquo;s hard to get passed the feeling that money has bought me a lot of happiness, which is a discomforting thing to think about. Or &amp;ndash; more accurately &amp;ndash; money has bought me a degree of independence I&amp;rsquo;ve never had, and that independence has allowed me the time and energy to spend on things that have made me more content&lt;a class=&#34;ref&#34; href=&#34;#ref-5&#34; id=&#34;cit-5&#34;&gt;[5]&lt;/a&gt; than I&amp;rsquo;ve been at any other point. It sounds nice to say that, beyond a baseline of basic necessities, money can&amp;rsquo;t buy happiness, but it just doesn&amp;rsquo;t seem true to me. Having &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.urbandictionary.com/define.php?term=fuck+you+money&amp;amp;defid=116444&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;fuck you&amp;rdquo; money&lt;/a&gt; seems to me to bring the opportunity for happiness on some level (not as a &lt;em&gt;literal&lt;/em&gt; fuck-you to anybody, but as a measure of dependence on work). This is a troubling notion, and hammers home for me just how privileged and lucky I&amp;rsquo;ve been.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;notes:fc84fea5310ea60ddb3b3c9b9d9b4ddc&#34;&gt;Notes&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li id=&#34;ref-1&#34;&gt;I was especially discouraged about one particular instance, where I&#39;d gotten to the third round only to get turned down :( It was at a really cool software company in New York (it was a remote position). They offered tuition reimbursement, whatever hardware I wanted, conference funds, and all kinds of cool stuff. Not to mention I would&#39;ve been working with a ton of really smart people. (I&#39;m not bitter...) &lt;a class=&#34;cit&#34; href=&#34;#cit-1&#34;&gt;&amp;crarr;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li id=&#34;ref-2&#34;&gt;More traveling. &lt;a class=&#34;cit&#34; href=&#34;#cit-2&#34;&gt;&amp;crarr;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li id=&#34;ref-3&#34;&gt;... who I&#39;m really jealous of. He&#39;s about to go visit family in Guam. Safe travels, Trevor! &lt;a class=&#34;cit&#34; href=&#34;#cit-3&#34;&gt;&amp;crarr;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li id=&#34;ref-4&#34;&gt;I don&#39;t mean to show off (yes I do), but I just found out today I was voted our CC section&#39;s assistant coach of the year. It&#39;s already going to my head. &lt;a class=&#34;cit&#34; href=&#34;#cit-4&#34;&gt;&amp;crarr;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li id=&#34;ref-5&#34;&gt;I guess I would have a hard time justifying the claim that I&#39;m happier in general than at any other point in my life, but I feel comfortable saying that I&#39;m more content. &lt;a class=&#34;cit&#34; href=&#34;#cit-5&#34;&gt;&amp;crarr;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    
    
    <item>
      <title>African grey international trade banned</title>
      <link>https://natedobbins.net/birds/african-grey-global-trade-banned.html</link>
      
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Oct 2016</pubDate>
      <author>Nate Dobbins</author>
      <guid>https://natedobbins.net/birds/african-grey-global-trade-banned.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Today is a day to celebrate for bird lovers. Today, all international trade in African grey parrots is now banned thanks to the &lt;a href=&#34;https://cites.org/cop17&#34;&gt;Convention on International Trade in Endangered Species&lt;/a&gt; (CITES) in Johannesburg, where the 182 member nations ultimately voted in favor of giving greys the highest level of protection.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure class=&#34;left large&#34;&gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/97f30e593f2e2dca719dc3d385122ada432e823a/0_356_5315_3189/master/5315.jpg?w=620&amp;amp;q=55&amp;amp;auto=format&amp;amp;usm=12&amp;amp;fit=max&amp;amp;s=e713da3cb857bdf132c0443143ff0153&#34; alt=&#34;FLUFFY.&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
        FLUFFY.
        
            
        
        &lt;/p&gt; 
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://cites.org/sites/default/files/ndf_material/WG6-CS1.pdf&#34;&gt;According to CITES&lt;/a&gt;, about 21% of wild greys are harvested every year, and 60%+ die somewhere in the process of being captured and transported to market. Right now, the wild African grey population is estimated to be &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.parrots.org/encyclopedia/grey-parrot&#34;&gt;around 560,000&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bird lovers often cite &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=SzPiTwDE0bE&#34;&gt;Dr. Irene Pepperberg&amp;rsquo;s work with Alex&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; a Congo African grey &amp;ndash; as seminal work on bird intelligence generally, and also as evidence for the argument to protect grey populations in the wild.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The full proposal presented at CITES can be found &lt;a href=&#34;https://cites.org/sites/default/files/eng/cop/17/prop/060216/E-CoP17-Prop-19.pdf&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. Formally, what was voted on was whether to transfer greys from CITES Appendix II to Appendix I (&lt;a href=&#34;https://cites.org/eng/app/appendices.php&#34;&gt;appendices explanation here&lt;/a&gt;). Note that the new rules apply to both Congo and Timneh African greys.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m guessing this was most greys&amp;rsquo; reaction to the news:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;iframe class=&#34;fit&#34; type=&#34;text/html&#34; width=&#34;640&#34; height=&#34;385&#34;
  src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/WecS9-3ISkk&#34; allowfullscreen
  frameborder=&#34;0&#34;/&gt;
&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    
    
    <item>
      <title>The Mobile Computer I Want</title>
      <link>https://natedobbins.net/computers/the-mobile-computer-i-want.html</link>
      
      <pubDate>Sun, 24 Jul 2016</pubDate>
      <author>Nate Dobbins</author>
      <guid>https://natedobbins.net/computers/the-mobile-computer-i-want.html</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;My phone has been bumming me out lately. I&amp;rsquo;ve decided to fantasize about my ideal mobile computer, a rough description of which is as follows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&#34;right&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://pyra-handheld.com/boards/pyrapics/pyrared.png&#34; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;https://pyra-handheld.com/boards/pages/pyra/&#34;&gt;Dragonbox Pyra&lt;/a&gt; comes pretty close to everything I want. The original Dragonbox device, the &lt;a href=&#34;https://pyra-handheld.com/boards/pages/pandora/&#34;&gt;Pandora&lt;/a&gt;, was released in 2008 and still receives OS updates, and you can still buy any replacement parts needed.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;screen:9c931dc12966c06dc1212525a5e987c2&#34;&gt;Screen&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m ready to be done with back-lit, full-color, battery-busting displays. My ideal computer would have a 5&amp;rdquo;-6&amp;rdquo; front-lit e-ink display, ideally in color. Color e-ink has suffered through various fits and starts over the last 5 or so years, most recently being &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pcmag.com/news/344735/e-ink-shows-off-full-color-display&#34;&gt;announced&lt;/a&gt; by E Ink (the company) for digital signage at the SID Display Week exhibition in May. There are some obvious use-cases that e-ink isn&amp;rsquo;t well-suited for (watching videos, playing fast-paced games), but the things that e-ink &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; good for (reading and writing text) is exactly what I want my computer to encourage me to do more of. (Besides, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=CWZfU_21ZbI&#34;&gt;Sonic the Hedgehog running on a Nook Simple Touch from 2011&lt;/a&gt; has me not too worried about actual refresh rate when I want to watch a video or something.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;cpu-and-antennas:9c931dc12966c06dc1212525a5e987c2&#34;&gt;CPU and Antennas&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are some &lt;a href=&#34;https://imgur.com/a/J0P5n&#34;&gt;cool mini-computers&lt;/a&gt; that use a Raspberry Pi, and that was where my intuition took me first. But for my main computer, I&amp;rsquo;d like something a little bit more powerful and flexible. Although it&amp;rsquo;s not finished yet, the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lowrisc.org/&#34;&gt;lowRISC&lt;/a&gt; system-on-a-chip seems to be just about the perfect candidate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&#34;left&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://global.blackberry.com/content/dam/blackberry-com/images/smartphones/blackberry-priv/specifications/3.png&#34; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;The Blackberry Priv, Blackberry&#39;s first phone not running BBOS. The &lt;a href=&#34;http://pocketnow.com/2015/11/13/8-fun-blackberry-priv-features#toc-6&#34;&gt;keyboard doubles as a trackpad&lt;/a&gt; for swiping and moving the cursor in text areas, as with other recent Blackberry phones. The lack of removable battery is the main thing that kept me from getting it.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For antennas, my computer would only have WiFi, GPS, and accelerometer onboard. There would also be a separate USB module (or a couple) for FM radio, bluetooth, NFC, SIM card, and cellular antennas. (A camera and microphone would also be in a separate USB module.) I prefer to keep it lean with only the necessities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;ports:9c931dc12966c06dc1212525a5e987c2&#34;&gt;Ports&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All the ports! I want to be able to hook up an external keyboard, mouse, and display to put together whatever workspace I want as a &amp;ldquo;dumb terminal&amp;rdquo; that plugs into my computer. Microsoft and Canonical have notably been pushing in this direction recently (with Windows 10 and Unity 8, respectively), and the Dragonbox devices are perfectly suited to it. Luckily, we don&amp;rsquo;t need any new technology to pull it off, we just need to revert the trend of fewer and fewer ports on computers. This sort of setup obviously can&amp;rsquo;t cater to everybody (AAA gamers, people compiling big codebases, people using CAD), but I think it could be a big step when we can realistically only own one computer and connect it to various workspace configurations, rather than having some combination of smartphone, tablet, laptop, desktop, work computer, smart TV, and game console&amp;ndash;all with their own CPUs. Movement in this direction would make different computing environments cheaper and more accessible (for people who now can only afford a smartphone, for example).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&#34;right&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://www.wired.com/wp-content/uploads/2016/02/fairphone-gallery05-1024x768.jpg&#34; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;The Fairphone 2 is the only smartphone to ever receive a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ifixit.com/Teardown/Fairphone+2+Teardown/52523&#34;&gt;10/10 repairability score from iFixit&lt;/a&gt;. Fairphone (a Dutch company) is also the only smartphone producer that I&#39;m aware of that uses only conflict-free materials in its phones.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Specifically, I&amp;rsquo;d like to have a couple USB-B slots (either USB 2 or 3), one or two USB-C slots, ethernet, HDMI (either micro or full-size), and a 3.5mm headset port.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;modularity:9c931dc12966c06dc1212525a5e987c2&#34;&gt;Modularity&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Upgradeability, durability, and repairability are of the utmost importance for my computer. It should take heed from computers like older ThinkPads, the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.fairphone.com/&#34;&gt;Fairphone&lt;/a&gt; 2, and the DragonBox Pyra. It should encourage the replacement of the battery (which should be giant, by the way), and make accessible each of the other boards, sealed only by Phillips screws. This thing should be built to last on the scale of one to two decades (or more).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;keyboard:9c931dc12966c06dc1212525a5e987c2&#34;&gt;Keyboard&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although software keyboards have made significant gains in the last few years (mostly by getting creative with swiping), they&amp;rsquo;re still woefully inferior to hardware keyboards. The effect this has on defining the purpose of a device is massive; getting any kind of productive work done with a software keyboard is left only to a dedicated few. For most intents and purposes, it just won&amp;rsquo;t cut it. This leaves keyboardless smartphones and tablets fully in the realm of devices made for consumption.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&#34;left&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/kindle-dx-is-back.jpg&#34; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;The Amazon Kindle DX, from 2009, with a giant 10 inch e-ink display ticks a few of my boxes, but is no longer available new.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although I&amp;rsquo;d like to have some room for consumption (long texts, blog posts, music, and podcasts come to mind), I want my computer to cater to creativity and productivity. The current market for devices that fill this niche is underwhelming, to say the least. On my computer, the keyboard would sit under the portrait-situated screen (i.e. not a slider). It would have the full set of keys from full-sized keyboards, and would include the ability to swipe across the keyboard to move the cursor (shamelessly stolen from recent Blackberry keyboards).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;software:9c931dc12966c06dc1212525a5e987c2&#34;&gt;Software&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The duopoly in mobile operating systems has left us with gimped computers that are meant to favor app stores over the open web (and&amp;ndash;to beat a dead horse&amp;ndash;to encourage consumption). My computer would start with &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.coreboot.org/&#34;&gt;coreboot&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&#34;https://libreboot.org/&#34;&gt;libreboot&lt;/a&gt;, and allow the user to use whichever OS they&amp;rsquo;d prefer. By default, it&amp;rsquo;d perhaps come with either Debian or rooted Android (probably of the &lt;a href=&#34;https://copperhead.co&#34;&gt;Copperhead OS&lt;/a&gt; variety) for ease of use. Regardless, allowing the user to have full control over the software is paramount.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The monoculture of smartphone and tablet design is disappointing. The dominance of iOS and Android&amp;ndash;to the exclusion of most other competitors like Blackberry, Windows, Mozilla, Jolla&amp;ndash;does no one any favors (well, no end users at least). At least among my peers in my generation, it would seem very strange to most if someone didn&amp;rsquo;t have either an Android or iOS phone, let alone if someone didn&amp;rsquo;t carry a smartphone at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My main beef with this situation is that almost all of these phones are unabashedly computers meant for consumption and convenience over all else. Whereas computers with hardware keyboards and many ports and bigger screens are as effective of tools for creativity as they are for consumption, our modern slabs mostly hinder any chances for creativity (or, at least, they offer no where near the capacity for productivity that the aforementioned computers do). What I was really thinking about when describing my ideal mobile computer is how I could combine all of the benefits of laptops, e-readers, and smartphones into one. I want to have as much power as I do on my laptop with the portability of my smartphone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the web, we&amp;rsquo;ve seen a long and gradual shift toward the centralization of content and services at the server level (AWS) and the service level (Facebook, Google, etc.), instead of the spreading out of power. ISPs have increasingly exerted more control and made it impractical to run any type of server at home (the suggestion itself sounds almost absurd) by reducing upload times to near zero, and blocking ports needed to run home servers. To me, this gradual centralization of web services and inability to run servers from home seems parallel and analogous to the gradual shift toward computers that are useful only for consumption.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In one sense, it&amp;rsquo;s wonderful that cheap smartphones have enabled so many to access the web. I should note that I wouldn&amp;rsquo;t suggest that all consumption is necessarily a bad thing. For example, access to information via Wikipedia, books via Project Gutenberg, classes via Khan Academy, repair tutorials via iFixit, and countless other sources can all be wonderful modes of consumption. But, it seems like as our devices cater more and more toward consumption and reliance on centralized services (rather than productivity and independence), the feedback loop that centralizes services will only be added to, empowering manufacturers and service providers at the expense of users.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    
    
    <item>
      <title>At Home, Fixing Things</title>
      <link>https://natedobbins.net/computers/at-home-fixing-things.html</link>
      
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 May 2016</pubDate>
      <author>Nate Dobbins</author>
      <guid>https://natedobbins.net/computers/at-home-fixing-things.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m home! I got back the first week of May, and have been hanging out in Rochester since. It&amp;rsquo;s been nice and relaxing, but I&amp;rsquo;m moving back up to St. Paul on June 1st.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my last week in Thailand, my laptop started refusing to boot up (&lt;code&gt;FAN ERROR.&lt;/code&gt;), and a tiny crack appeared on my phone screen and gradually turned into a big crack, rendering it unable to pick up most touches and swipes. Evidently the computing gods were angry that I was leaving the Land of Australian Expats, but I figured I&amp;rsquo;d give a shot at fixing them since they&amp;rsquo;re both only a couple years old. I&amp;rsquo;m not sure what caused either of the problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The laptop (a 2013 ThinkPad X1 Carbon) would display the ThinkPad splash screen, then give a beep inform me that there was a &lt;code&gt;FAN ERROR&lt;/code&gt;. I couldn&amp;rsquo;t get into BIOS. After a big of googling, it was pretty apparent that I&amp;rsquo;m not the first to run into this issue. Seems that it&amp;rsquo;s a normal thing among various 2008-2014 X and T series (at least) ThinkPads. Unfortunately the usual advice seemed to be either replace the fan or blow on the fan exhaust port to trick it into booting up, after which you&amp;rsquo;d have to monitor the system temperature (&amp;hellip;). I tried the blowing thing and couldn&amp;rsquo;t get it to work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;d somewhat regretted getting an ultrabook for a while since it&amp;rsquo;s just short of impossible to replace most parts, and I was again cursing my judgment since I figured it&amp;rsquo;d be a mess if I tried to get the fan out of there. But I decided to open it up and take a look.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;https://c3.staticflickr.com/8/7547/27125755442_e1cd5a7335_z.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;There were 7 Phillips head screws holding the case together, and you have to pull the keyboard side up, which threw me off for a minute. The fan is the circular thing underneath the copper-colored thing.&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
        There were 7 Phillips head screws holding the case together, and you have to pull the keyboard side up, which threw me off for a minute. The fan is the circular thing underneath the copper-colored thing.
        
            
        
        &lt;/p&gt; 
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I manually spun the fan around a couple times and noticed that at a certain point in the rotation it seemed to get stuck on something. There was no way to look at what it was without removing the fan glue, but I manually spun it around a few more times, and blew compressed air around the whole board, which seemed to dislodge whatever the fan was stuck on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After this the computer magically booted up again. Hopefully this will be helpful to a future googler who&amp;rsquo;s about to smash their ThinkPad over their head.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Replacing the screen on my phone (an LG G3) promises to be a bit more work. Luckily iFixit has &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ifixit.com/Guide/LG+G3+Screen+Replacement/33203&#34;&gt;an awesome guide&lt;/a&gt; for exactly this. I just need to get around to ordering the parts and tools.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Two months on Isles de Malaysia</title>
      <link>https://natedobbins.net/travel/two-months-on-malaysian-islands.html</link>
      
      <pubDate>Sat, 23 Apr 2016</pubDate>
      <author>Nate Dobbins</author>
      <guid>https://natedobbins.net/travel/two-months-on-malaysian-islands.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Whew. What&amp;rsquo;s new? Not much. Here are some pictures:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1463/26528965131_ca31975c00_z.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;It turns out George Town is known for street art.&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
        It turns out George Town is known for street art.
        
            
        
        &lt;/p&gt; 
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1535/25860601080_41204f8844_z.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1689/26107381166_c0a473a3bb_z.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Hiking in Penang.&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
        Hiking in Penang.
        
            
        
        &lt;/p&gt; 
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1545/26321811520_d905718d3c_z.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Langkawi beaches.&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
        Langkawi beaches.
        
            
        
        &lt;/p&gt; 
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;More pictures &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/133041204@N06/albums/72157666499077326&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/133041204@N06/sets/72157665162128674&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coastal Malaysia is well-suited to relaxing and staring out to sea. In Penang I did some hiking and ferried to the mainland to see a bird pirk, which was pretty much the same thing as KL bird park, but it was cool. The beaches and parks are nice. Usually I end up stuck inside during the afternoon, though, &amp;lsquo;cause it&amp;rsquo;s really hot. I spent March and half of April in George Town (the main city on Penang), and then took a ferry north to Langkawi. The ferry was a little bit disappointing; I was stuck in the lower level and the fiberglass windows were too dirty to see out of. But they played a VHS of the new Ip Man so it was cool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The food in Langkawi is really, really good. The place I&amp;rsquo;m staying is about a fifteen minute walk outside of town, which is pretty much just one main street. So it&amp;rsquo;s a little more laid back here than any of the other main places I&amp;rsquo;ve stayed so far. The island is duty free, so there&amp;rsquo;s lots alcohol and cigarettes and chocolate everywhere. There are also lots of Germans here ¯\&lt;em&gt;(ツ)&lt;/em&gt;/¯&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Monday I&amp;rsquo;m going to Phuket, an island further north. I&amp;rsquo;ll be there for about 10 days then I&amp;rsquo;ll be re-joining the American proletariat. Peace!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    
    
    <item>
      <title>A Month in Chiang Mai</title>
      <link>https://natedobbins.net/travel/a-month-in-chiang-mai.html</link>
      
      <pubDate>Sun, 28 Feb 2016</pubDate>
      <author>Nate Dobbins</author>
      <guid>https://natedobbins.net/travel/a-month-in-chiang-mai.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;If heaven is a place on earth, it&amp;rsquo;s Chiang Mai, Thailand. I&amp;rsquo;ve spent the month of February not really doing much. Chiang Mai is well suited to leisurely lounging around town.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chiang Mai is situated in a valley, so the climate is more pleasant than a lot of the region. The surrounding bluffs make for a lot of great hiking. I made the trip west of town to Doi Suthep national park four times, in search of hiking and birds. I wasn&amp;rsquo;t able to spot any weird birds but the waterfalls and hiking were good.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1551/24490478574_cf7fe137f2_c.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;A temple halfway up Doi Suthep Mountain.&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
        A temple halfway up Doi Suthep Mountain.
        
            
        
        &lt;/p&gt; 
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In the center of the city is a walled area surrounded by a moat, 1.6 km on each side. Inside the walled &amp;ldquo;old city&amp;rdquo; are lots of temples and stores and cafes. My guesthouse was situated a couple blocks south of the southern gate to the old city. There&amp;rsquo;s a fresh food market at the gate, and tons of street food stalls in the evenings, so I ate most of my meals there, seated next to the moat. I ate mostly sushi and smoothies.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1516/24869934485_0c1ebce914_c.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;A moat outside the old city south gate.&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
        A moat outside the old city south gate.
        
            
        
        &lt;/p&gt; 
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Almost every street in Chiang Mai is lined with little shops and cafes and bars. In the evenings there&amp;rsquo;s live music coming from everywhere, and on the weekends there are &amp;ldquo;walking markets&amp;rdquo; in a couple locations, usually crowded beyond belief. There also seem to be music stores and instrument shops all over town.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1605/24494317643_165f797e57_c.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I got breakfast and lunch at a coffee shop near the guesthouse a bunch because it was cheap and the lady that worked there gave me the scoop about all the places I need to visit. Usually I was the only person there but the second-to-last time I went there were a couple Americans debating whether &lt;sup&gt;9&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;11&lt;/sub&gt; was an inside job. &lt;em&gt;Yay America&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The full Chiang Mai photo album is available &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/133041204@N06/sets/72157663697447279&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tomorrow morning it&amp;rsquo;s onwards and upwards to the island of Penang, Malaysia. I really need to get to bed but I can&amp;rsquo;t stop watching Rick and Morty.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Adventures in Phantosmia</title>
      <link>https://natedobbins.net/story/adventures-in-phantosmia.html</link>
      
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Feb 2016</pubDate>
      <author>Nate Dobbins</author>
      <guid>https://natedobbins.net/story/adventures-in-phantosmia.html</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;I recently read &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/1297985.Musicophilia&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Musicophilia: Tales of Music and the Brain&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; by Oliver Sacks. Chapter 6 was on a phenomenon called &amp;ldquo;musical hallucinations.&amp;rdquo; In contrast with musical imagery, where a person imagines the sound of music in her head, musical hallucinations entail truly feeling like you&amp;rsquo;re hearing music. According to the book, brain scans show that people experiencing musical hallucinations show the same brain activity activity as those actually listening to music. Some who suffer from musical hallucinations are entirely unable to rid themselves of constant and uncontrollable music, to the point that their lives can be overwhelmed by it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve never experienced this, but reading it did remind me of an experience I had during the winter of 2010-&amp;lsquo;11, where I hallucinated a smell. I was in the last couple miles of a 16 mile run with my cross country team on a cold winter morning. We were running by a community center off Marshall Avenue in St. Paul, and I smelled the strongest scent of bubble gum I&amp;rsquo;d ever smelled. It was quite pleasant. But my mouth was seemingly frozen solid so I didn&amp;rsquo;t mention it until we finished the run and I had a chance to unthaw. To my surprise, nobody else had noticed the scent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&#34;left&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;http://www.nhs.uk/Conditions/phantosmia/PublishingImages/phantosmia_342x198_136598104.jpg&#34; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;The top Google image result for &#34;phantosmia.&#34;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had all but forgotten about this experience until I read &lt;em&gt;Musicophilia&lt;/em&gt;. I decided to dig in to see what the web had to say about hallucinating smells. Apparently it&amp;rsquo;s called &amp;ldquo;Phantosmia&amp;rdquo;, and usually it&amp;rsquo;s an unpleasant smell, according to the UK&amp;rsquo;s NHS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wikipedia assures me that phantosmia &amp;ldquo;often occurs with neurological and psychological disorders such as schizophrenia, mood disorders, Parkinsons disease, epilepsy, neuroblastoma, and frequent migranes,&amp;rdquo; so I&amp;rsquo;ve got nothing to worry about. Mayoclinic.org also paints a bright picture: &amp;ldquo;Phantosmia may occur after a head injury or upper respiratory infection. It can also be caused by temporal lobe seizures, inflamed sinuses, brain tumors and Parkinson&amp;rsquo;s disease.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t recall suffering any brain injuries (then again, who remembers suffering a brain injury?), so I&amp;rsquo;m going to chalk it up to being toward the tail end of an endurance workout and being affected by the cold temperature. Regardless, I&amp;rsquo;ll be on the lookout for further signs of temporal lobe seizures and brain tumors. I had forgotten about the hallucination until I read the book; I think this is a pretty good argument for not reading anymore, lest I uncover further signs of brain damage hidden from my memory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;what-s-new:5a95fc7849e03bda044151e45d0a325b&#34;&gt;What&amp;rsquo;s new&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s 3:44am and I&amp;rsquo;m writing this post in an airport cafeteria waiting for a restaurant called Toast Box to open at 4. In a couple hours I&amp;rsquo;m flying from Kuala Lumpur to Chiang Mai, Thailand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For my last month or so in KL, I didn&amp;rsquo;t do a whole lot. Lots of relaxing and slowly lounging around town. I started working on software to make building websites easier with two close friends and former co-workers. (&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/topiary-io/topiary&#34;&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s here.&lt;/a&gt;) KL has been great, but saying I&amp;rsquo;m excited to get out would be an understatement. I&amp;rsquo;m ready for something a bit smaller, and I&amp;rsquo;m ready for a hotel room with windows.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Holiday in Cambodia</title>
      <link>https://natedobbins.net/travel/holiday-in-malaysia.html</link>
      
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Dec 2015</pubDate>
      <author>Nate Dobbins</author>
      <guid>https://natedobbins.net/travel/holiday-in-malaysia.html</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=-KTsXHXMkJA&#34;&gt;Reference and soundtrack for this post.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve been in Kuala Lumpur for just over a month now. As I alluded to in my last post, lately I&amp;rsquo;ve been taking the free KL city bus around almost everyday, and seeing more of the city. I&amp;rsquo;ve been to Petronas Twin Towers, Menara Kuala Lumpur, back to Lake Gardens, and a bunch of malls like Low Yat (an &amp;ldquo;IT lifestyle mall&amp;rdquo;), KLCC, and Berjaya Times Square. Most of these are in the Golden Triangle and Bukit Bintang areas, a couple miles east of my hostel.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5781/23492187489_4788811c33_c.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Petronas Twin Towers&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
        Petronas Twin Towers
        
            
        
        &lt;/p&gt; 
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Last week I went to the US Embassy to get some extra passport pages, which is a service that is apparently ceasing after January 1st. It felt like a DMV.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve been catching up on podcasts that I fell behind on, mostly while walking around the malls and riding the bus. I also saw the new James Bond movie the other day, and I&amp;rsquo;ll probably see Star Wars soon, like the obedient consumer that I am. OH! and I just found out there&amp;rsquo;s a new Charlie Kaufman movie called Anomalisa that opens next month. I&amp;rsquo;m not sure if I&amp;rsquo;ll be able to see it in Malaysia but I&amp;rsquo;ll be keeping an eye out.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;https://farm1.staticflickr.com/755/23492192339_a37868d77c_c.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Relaxing at Lake Gardens.&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
        Relaxing at Lake Gardens.
        
            
        
        &lt;/p&gt; 
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Christmas in Malaysia—it turns out—is serious business. Everywhere I turn, including in my hostel lounge, there are brightly adorned Christmas trees and smiling Santas and plastic snowmen. Especially in the Golden Triangle (aka the Central Business District), it feels very much like the wonderfully commercial sales-month that I&amp;rsquo;m used to in the US. (There&amp;rsquo;s nothing like a good deal on TVs to make me feel all warm and fuzzy.) This despite the fact that &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Christianity_in_Malaysia&#34;&gt;only 9.2% of Malaysians are Christian&lt;/a&gt;. It &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; a public holiday here, but apparently it&amp;rsquo;s only celebrated on Christmas Eve, and then it&amp;rsquo;s business-as-usual on the 25th.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;https://farm1.staticflickr.com/675/23860121355_f1da845760_c.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;A giant Christmas tree outside KLCC.&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
        A giant Christmas tree outside KLCC.
        
            
        
        &lt;/p&gt; 
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You can see the full photo album of things from the last month &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/133041204@N06/sets/72157661890074839&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;resolutions:23ac1a3c3444fb682e0a8476884c6aee&#34;&gt;Resolutions&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;New Year&amp;rsquo;s resolutions are silly. Here are mine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Write&lt;/strong&gt; I want to get better at writing. About techy stuff, thinky stuff, and bloggy stuff. At the moment I have 7 half-written blog posts in my drafts folder about tech/web/software, so part one of my resolution is to commit to finishing these posts and writing more in general. Also related to writing better, I need to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Read&lt;/strong&gt; Not that reading isn&amp;rsquo;t an end unto itself, but I want to read both for the sake of reading and of writing better. I&amp;rsquo;ve already been reading a lot more since arriving in Kuala Lumpur so part two of my resolution is to keep it up, and maybe even kick it up a gear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Meditate&lt;/strong&gt; I&amp;rsquo;ve tried to start meditating more times than I can count, and I never stick with it. Part three of my resolution is to stick with it. I want to think more clearly, stay more focused, and be more relaxed. I&amp;rsquo;m hoping meditation can be a step in that direction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s inevitably a lot more that I&amp;rsquo;m not including, but I think focusing on these three things will help me with all the other ones. Like all good New Year&amp;rsquo;s resolutions, it inevitably contains too much anyway, and is sure to collapse unto itself. Maybe I should just get a gym membership. ¯\_(ツ)_/¯&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Happy Festivus!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Adjusting and Batu Caves</title>
      <link>https://natedobbins.net/travel/adjusting-and-batu-caves.html</link>
      
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Nov 2015</pubDate>
      <author>Nate Dobbins</author>
      <guid>https://natedobbins.net/travel/adjusting-and-batu-caves.html</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve been in Kuala Lumpur for just under two weeks now, and I&amp;rsquo;m settling into a pretty comfortable routine. I usually divide my day into three parts: in one part I explore a new part of the city, in another I head to the library to code or read, and in the last I relax. In between I find some food. I switch up the arrangement of the parts each day. Just having a routine is nice, though, and it&amp;rsquo;s helping me adjust pretty well. In no particular order, here are some thoughts on adapting to various aspects of life in Malaysia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;language:8b21b83e3eb70520743ff76bb4cc09d3&#34;&gt;Language&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Getting down the basics of Bahasa Malay has been straightforward. Word order is subject-verb-object like English. It also borrows a lot of words from English (this is where Malay branches apart from Indonesian, which is closely related but borrows from Dutch). The writing system is &lt;strong&gt;very&lt;/strong&gt; phonetic, which is almost jarring coming from English. Most words are pronounced exactly how you&amp;rsquo;d guess when reading them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only problem is that almost everyone here speaks English (and I&amp;rsquo;m so white), so everyone defaults to English. That&amp;rsquo;s probably a good thing though, because I&amp;rsquo;d be lost beyond the basics. My aunt was right, though, when she said that most people would probably be thankful when I put a small effort into using Malay. Usually I just slip in a &lt;em&gt;terima kasih&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;selamat pagi&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;food:8b21b83e3eb70520743ff76bb4cc09d3&#34;&gt;Food&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It can&amp;rsquo;t be overstated how good the food is. And the food stalls and cafés are neverending! Just walking down random streets, I&amp;rsquo;ll often unintentionally wander into big street markets lined with the most wonderful-smelling food I could imagine. I&amp;rsquo;m glad I have another couple months in KL, because I&amp;rsquo;ve barely scratched the surface yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;getting-around:8b21b83e3eb70520743ff76bb4cc09d3&#34;&gt;Getting around&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So far, I&amp;rsquo;ve used the train to get from the airport to the city center, and to get to Batu Caves (more on that below). Other than that, I&amp;rsquo;ve just walked everywhere. Getting around on foot is pretty easy, but there are some areas where sidewalks are a little weird. Sometimes they&amp;rsquo;ll just end, or they&amp;rsquo;ll merge into the road. For awhile I would get confused and not know how to keep going in the general direction I was trying to go, until I realized that people would just walk on the road. This happens even on bigger roads where traffic is flying by, so it took me a bit to get used to, but now I&amp;rsquo;m on board. It&amp;rsquo;s evened out by the fact that drivers often park partially on the sidewalk, and motorcyclists (who are numerous!) often &lt;em&gt;drive&lt;/em&gt; on the sidewalks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve explored just about everywhere within a three kilometer radius of my hostel, so over the next couple weeks I&amp;rsquo;m going to start using the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.gokl.com.my/&#34;&gt;Go-KL&lt;/a&gt; city bus (because it&amp;rsquo;s free!) to start exploring more of the city.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;weather:8b21b83e3eb70520743ff76bb4cc09d3&#34;&gt;Weather&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The weather has been beautiful. In the morning it&amp;rsquo;s usually around 70 degrees and clear. From around 11 to 4 it gets very hot, and then it often rains in the late afternoon and evening. As I&amp;rsquo;m writing this, I&amp;rsquo;m just getting dried off, because even though an umbrella was the first thing I bought here, I never have the sense to bring my umbrella when I go out in the morning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;getting-connected:8b21b83e3eb70520743ff76bb4cc09d3&#34;&gt;Getting connected&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since I don&amp;rsquo;t have mobile data or a phone plan, I&amp;rsquo;ve been completely relient on wifi to stay connected. So far it&amp;rsquo;s proven pretty simple. The wifi at the hostel is good. The library also has wifi, although it&amp;rsquo;s not quite as reliable. Regardless, I haven&amp;rsquo;t run into any issues with needing internet and not being able to get it. I have three different mapping applications on my phone, and all three have the ability to download maps for offline use, which is killer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;batu-caves:8b21b83e3eb70520743ff76bb4cc09d3&#34;&gt;Batu Caves&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This morning I packed up a bag and hopped on the KTM Komuter red line heading north for Batu Caves. The caves are sunken into a giant limestone hill, and they&amp;rsquo;re marked by the statue of the Hindu Lord Murugan:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5777/23418089165_bc7f5bf939_c.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;It&amp;#39;s the tallest statue in Malaysia and the second tallest statue of a Hindu deity in the world.&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
        It&amp;#39;s the tallest statue in Malaysia and the second tallest statue of a Hindu deity in the world.
        
            
        
        &lt;/p&gt; 
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s one main cave, two slightly lesser ones, and many smaller caves. They&amp;rsquo;re filled with various shrines and smaller statues. To get to the main cave you have to climb up a steep flight of stairs (pictured above behind Murugan). Inside the main cave there&amp;rsquo;s a series of three large caverns, each with a shrine. The second cavern has a small crevice in the roof where light peeps through, and the third has a &lt;em&gt;huge&lt;/em&gt; opening through which the sky lights the cave. There&amp;rsquo;s also water seeping through the openings, dripping on unsuspecting heads at various points throughout the cave. There are also a few hens and pigeons scampering about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are the stairs leading up to the third cavern in the main cave:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;https://farm1.staticflickr.com/739/23122380170_23d3eeb083_z.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Inside the main cave.&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
        Inside the main cave.
        
            
        
        &lt;/p&gt; 
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Along the walkway outside the caves, there are lots of temples and galleries, lots of pigeons and monkeys, and lots of restaurants. I had lunch at a small Indian café, which seemed to insist on Coca-Cola with every dish, so I had a Coke. Outside there was a blue-and-gold macaw and a sulphur-crested cockatoo perched on a branch. They clearly weren&amp;rsquo;t wild, but they weren&amp;rsquo;t exactly pets, and it struck me how colorful and shiny their feathers were.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The full Batu Caves photo album is &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/133041204@N06/albums/72157661786697196&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    
  </channel>
</rss>

