<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Nate Dobbins writes things.</title>
    <generator uri="https://gohugo.io">Hugo</generator>
    <link>https://natedobbins.net</link>
    <language>en-us</language>
    
    
    <updated>Tue, 24 Nov 2015 00:00:00 UTC</updated>
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Arrival and KL Bird Park</title>
      <link>https://natedobbins.net/travel/arrival-and-kl-bird-park.html</link>
      
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Nov 2015</pubDate>
      <author>Nate Dobbins</author>
      <guid>https://natedobbins.net/travel/arrival-and-kl-bird-park.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I landed in Kuala Lumpur on Friday afternoon. The flights were excellent; Asian airlines always seem to me much nicer than American ones. From the airport I took a 30 minute train ride into KL&amp;rsquo;s Old City Centre district, and struggled for a couple hours to find my hostel in the rain. Once I did, I had to quickly figure out how to get cash, where to find food and an umbrella, and how to use my voltage converter to charge my phone. It was a rough first night, and I wasn&amp;rsquo;t as prepared as I should&amp;rsquo;ve been.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First impressions die hard (or something); everyday since has been great. The next day I woke up early to clear skies and had a delicious breakfast and tea at the hostel. I started exploring by foot and found that the traffic and sidewalks are much more manageable in the mornings. I found the beautiful &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Merdeka_Square,_Kuala_Lumpur&#34;&gt;Dataran Merdeka&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; (Independence Square), where Malaysian independence from Britain was declared in 1957. It&amp;rsquo;s surrounded by lots of really neat old colonial buildings. I also found a public library where I&amp;rsquo;ve been spending some time the last few days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ventured to the west side of the district, and found &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lake_Gardens,_Kuala_Lumpur&#34;&gt;Taman Tasik Perdana&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; (Lake Gardens), a giant park which contains—among other things—the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/133041204@N06/22793572549/in/album-72157660736018089/lightbox/&#34;&gt;National Planetarium&lt;/a&gt; and the KL Bird Park. &lt;strong&gt;Kuala Lumpur has a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.klbirdpark.com/&#34;&gt;bird park&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/strong&gt; There&amp;rsquo;s an entrance fee, so I came back a couple days later prepared to spend a whole morning there. Here are some pictures I took:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;https://farm1.staticflickr.com/575/22873062947_ed4c2abcf7_z.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;A playful red lorikeet in the World of Parrots area.&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
        A playful red lorikeet in the World of Parrots area.
        
            
        
        &lt;/p&gt; 
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5680/22899442319_f6b44eea17_z.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&amp;#34;Hey Frank, didja hear the one about the deaf cockatoo? Neither did he. /(^o^)/&amp;#34;&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
        &amp;#34;Hey Frank, didja hear the one about the deaf cockatoo? Neither did he. /(^o^)/&amp;#34;
        
            
        
        &lt;/p&gt; 
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;https://farm1.staticflickr.com/699/22639075334_a588248774_z.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;The hornbills were one the most interesting birds there. I&amp;#39;d never seen one before.&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
        The hornbills were one the most interesting birds there. I&amp;#39;d never seen one before.
        
            
        
        &lt;/p&gt; 
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Right after I took the picture above, a couple people approached me and asked if I&amp;rsquo;d be interested in doing an interview. They were filming some sort of Malaysia PSA, as best as I can tell. They were incredibly nice, and asked a lot about where I was from and what I thought about Kuala Lumpur.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5819/22639064524_887d93cae6_z.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;This grey whistled with me for a bit.&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
        This grey whistled with me for a bit.
        
            
        
        &lt;/p&gt; 
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The full album of photos I took at KL Bird Park is &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/133041204@N06/albums/72157661467887295&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I haven&amp;rsquo;t ventured too far outside the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki/Kuala_Lumpur/Central&#34;&gt;Old City Centre&lt;/a&gt; yet. There&amp;rsquo;s so much to see on every block that there&amp;rsquo;s no need to! Some more pictures are &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/133041204@N06/albums/72157660736018089&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other things of note:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Traffic is crazy. I don&amp;rsquo;t remember it being like this in Phnom Penh. Trying to cross the street is terrifying (even at a crosswalk).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The markets and the food are amazing. Just as cool (and cheap!) as they&amp;rsquo;re reputed to be. And I haven&amp;rsquo;t even been to any night markets yet, which KL is known for.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I wasn&amp;rsquo;t sure what to expect from my first time staying in a hostel. My room is tiny and windowless, the showers are cold, and the building is more than a bit rundown. But the proprieters and other guests have all been quite nice, there&amp;rsquo;s free breakfast and coffee and tea, the building is air conditioned, it&amp;rsquo;s centrally located, and it feels safe and secure. And regardless, the price of hostels here is incredibly low for what you get, so I&amp;rsquo;m very happy so far.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Do yourself a favor and don&amp;rsquo;t look at &lt;a href=&#34;http://fahrinfo.vbb.de/bin/help.exe/dn?L=vs_mobilitymap&amp;amp;tpl=fullmap&amp;amp;tabApp=show&#34;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&#34;http://brunoimbrizi.com/experiments/#/07&#34;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; if you have things to do.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    
  </channel>
</rss>

